was. CHAPTER 12 MIGHT I HAVE A BIT OF EARTH?" Mary ran so fast that she was
rather out of breath when she reached her room. Her hair was ruffled on her
forehead and her cheeks were bright pink.
Her dinner was waiting on the table, and Martha was waiting near it that's a bit
late," she said. "Where hast thou been?" "I've seen Dickon!" said Mary. "I've seen
Dickon!" "I knew he'd come," said Martha exultantly. "How does thou like him?" "I
think— —I think he's beautiful!" said Mary in a determined voice. Martha looked
rather taken aback but she looked pleased, too. "Well," she said, "he's the best lad as
ever was born, but us never thought he was handsome. His nose turns up too much."
"I like it to turn up," said Mary and his eyes is so round," said Martha, a trifle
doubtful. "Though there are nice color." "I like them round," said Mary. "And they are
exactly the color of the sky over the mo Martha beamed with
satisfaction. "Mother says he made him that color with always look looking up
at the birds and the clouds. But he has got a big mouth, hasn't he,
now?" "I love his big mouth," said Mary obstinately. "I wish mine would just like
it." Martha chuckled delightedly it would look rare and funny
in thy bit of a face," she said. "But I
knowed it would be that way when I saw him. How did they like the seeds and the
garden tools?" "How did you know he brought them?"
asked Mary. "Eh! I never thought of him not bringing them He'd be sure to bring them
if they was in Yorkshire. He's such a trusty lad." Mary was afraid that she might begin
to ask difficult questions, but she did not. She was very much interested in the
seeds and gardening tools, and there was only one moment when Mary was
frightened. This was when she began to ask where the flowers were to be planted.
"Who did thou ask about it?" she inquired. "I haven't asked anybody yet," said Mary,
hesitating. "Well, I wouldn't ask the head Garder He's too grand, Mr. Roach
is." "I've never seen him," said Mary. "I've only seen underg gardeners and Ben weather
staff If I was you, I'd ask Ben weather staff advised Martha HEK not half as bad
as he looks, for all he's so crapped Mr. Craven lets him do what he
likes because he was here when Mrs.
Craven was alive and he used to make her laugh. She liked him. Perhaps he'd find
you a corner somewhere out of the way." "If it was out of the way and no one
wanted it, no one could mind my having it, could they?" Mary said
anxiously. "There wouldn't be no reason," answered Martha. "You wouldn't do no
harm." Mary ate her dinner as quickly as she could and when she rose from the
table she was going to run to her room to put on her hat again, but Martha stopped
her. "I've got something to tell you," she said. "I thought I'd let you eat your
dinner first. Mr. Craven came back this morning and I think he wants to see you."
Mary turned quite pale. "Oh!" she said. "Why!
Why! He didn't want to see me when I came.
I heard Pier say he didn't." "Well," explained Martha, "Mrs. Medlock
says it's because her mother. She was walking to th village and she met him.
She'd never spoke to him before, but Mrs.
Craven had been to our cottage two or three times. He'd forgot, but mother
hadn't and she made bold to stop him. I don't know what she said to him about
you but she said something has put him in the mind to see you before he goes
away again tomorrow Oh!" cried Mary Mar is he going away tomorrow I am so glad!" "He's
going for a long time. He may come back till autumn or winter. He's going to
travel in foreign places. He's always doing it." "Oh! I'm so glad— —so glad!" said Mary
thankfully. If he did not come back until winter, or even autumn, there would be
time to watch the secret garden come alive. Even if found out then and took it
away from her she would have had that much at
least. "When do you think he will want to see—" She did not finish the sentence,
because the door opened, and Mrs. Medlock walked in. She had on her best black
dress and cap, and her collar was fastened with a large brooch with a
picture of a man's face on it. It was a colored photograph of Mr. Medlock who had
died years years ago, and she always wore it when she was dressed up. She looked nervous and
excited. "Your hair's rough," she said quickly. "Go and brush it. Martha, help her
to slip on her best dress. Mr. Craven sent me to bring her to him in his
study." All the pink left Mary's cheeks.
Her heart began to thump and she felt herself changing into a stiff, plain,
silent child again. She did not even answer to Mrs. Medlock, but turned and
walked into her bedroom, followed by Martha. She said nothing while her dress
was changed, and her hair brushed, and after she was quite tidy she followed
Mrs. Medlock down the corridors, in silence. What was there for her to
say? She was obliged to go and see Mr.
Craven and he would not like her, and she would not like
him. She knew what he would think of her.
She was taken to a part of the house she had not been into
before. At last Mrs. Medlock knocked at a door, and when someone said, "Come in," they
entered the room together. A man was sitting in an armchair before the fire, and Mrs. Medlock
spoke to him. "This is Miss Mary, sir," she said. "You
can go and leave her here. I will ring
for you when I want you to take her away," said Mr.
Craven. When she went out and closed the door, Mary could only stand waiting, a
plain little thing, twisting her thin hands together. She could see that the man in
the chair was not so much a hunchback as a man with high, rather crooked
shoulders, and he had black hair stre with white. He turned his head over his
high shoulders and spoke to her. "Come here!" he said. Mary went to him.
He was not ugly. His face would have been handsome if it had not been so
miserable. He looked as if the sight of her worried and fretted him and as if he
did not know what in the world to do with her. "Are you well?" he asked. "Yes,"
answered Mary. "Do they take good care of you?" "Yes." He rubbed his forehead fretfully
as he looked her over. "You are very thin," he said. "I am getting fatter," Mary
answered in what she knew was her stiffest way. What an unhappy face he had!
His black eyes seemed as if they scarcely saw her, as if they were seeing
something else, and he could hardly keep his thoughts upon her. "I forgot you," he
said. "How could I remember you? I intended to send you a governance or a nurse, or
someone of that sort, but I forgot." "Please," began Mary. "Please—" and then
the lump in her throat choked her. "What do you want to say?" he
inquired. "I am— —I am too big for a nurse," said Mary. "And please— —please don't make
me have a governess yet." He rubbed his forehead again and stared at
her. "That was what the soure woman said," he muttered absent-mindedly. Then Mary gathered a
scrap of courage. "Is she— —is she Martha's mother?" she
stammered. "Yes, I think so," he replied. "She knows about children," said Mary. "She has
12 She knows." He seemed to rouse himself.
"What do you want to do?" "I want to play out of doors," Mary answered, hoping that
her voice did not tremble. "I never liked it in India. It makes me hungry here, and
I'm getting fatter." He was watching her.
"Mrs saby said it would do you good.
Perhaps it will," he said. "She thought you had better get stronger before you had a
govern It makes me feel strong when I play and the wind comes over the more
argued Mary. "Where do you play?" he asked next. "Everywhere," gasped
Mary. "Martha's mother sent me a skipping rope I skip and run— —and I look about to
see if things are beginning to stick up out of the earth. I don't do any
harm." "Don't look so frightened," he said in a worried voice. "You could not do any
harm, a child like you! You may do what you
like." Mary put her hand up to her throat because she was afraid he might see the
excited lump which she felt jump into it.
She came a step nearer to him. "May I?" she said tremulously. Her anxious little face
seemed to worry him more than ever. "Don't look so frightened," he exclaimed. "Of
course you may. I am your guardian, though I am a poor one for any child. I cannot
give you time or attention. I am too ill, and wretched and
distracted; but I wish you to be happy and comfortable. I don't know anything about
children, but Mrs. Medlock is to see that you have all you
need. I sent for you today because Mrs saby said I ought to see you. Her
daughter had talked about you. She thought you needed fresh air and freedom and running
about." "She knows all about children," Mary said again in spite of herself. "She ought
to," said Mr. Craven. "I thought her rather bold to stop me on the moall but she
said— —Mrs. Craven had been kind to her." It seemed hard for him to speak his dead wife's
name. "She is a respectable woman.
Now I have seen you I think she said sensible things. Play out of doors as
much as you like. It's a big place and you may go where you like and amuse
yourself as you like. Is there anything you want?" as if a sudden thought had
struck him. "Do you want toys, books, dolls?" "Might I," quavered Mary, "might I have a bit of
earth?" In her eagerness she did not real realized how queer the words would sound
and that they were not the ones she had meant to say. Mr. Craven looked quite
startled. "Earth!" he repeated. "What do you mean?" "To plant seeds in— —to make things
grow— —to see them come alive," Mary faltered. He gazed at her a moment and
then passed his hand quickly over his eyes. "Do you— —care about gardens so much,"
he said slowly.
"I didn't know about them in India," said Mary. "I was always ill and tired and it
was too hot. I sometimes made little beds in the sand and stuck flowers in them.
But here it is different." Mr. Craven got up and began to walk slowly across the
room. "A bit of earth," he said to himself, and Mary thought that somehow she must
have reminded him of something. When he stopped and spoke to her his dark eyes
looked almost soft and kind. "You can have as much earth as you
want," he said. "You remind me of someone else who loved the earth and things that
grow. When you see a bit of earth you want," with something like a
smile, "take it, child, and make it come alive." "May I take it from anywhere— —if
it's not wanted?" "Anywhere," he answered.
"There! You must go now, I am tired." He touched the bell to call Mrs. Medlock
goodbye I shall be away all summer." Mrs. Medlock came so quickly that
Mary thought she must have been waiting in the corridor. "Mrs. Medlock," Mr. Craven said to
her, "now I have seen the child I understand what Mrs saby meant.
She must be less delicate before she begins lessons. Give her simple, healthy food.
Let her run wild in the garden. Don't look after her too much. She needs
liberty and fresh air and romping about.
Mrs sby is to come and see her now and then and she may sometimes go to the
cottage." Mrs. Medlock looked pleased. She was relieved to hear that she need not
"look after" Mary too much. She had felt her a tiresome charge and had indeed
seen as little of her as she dared. In addition to this she was fond of Martha's
mother. "Thank you, sir," she said. "Susan sby and me went to school together and she's
as sensible and good-hearted a woman as you'd find in a day's walk. I never had
any children myself and she's had 12 and there never was healthier or better ones.
Miss Mary can get no harm from them. I'd always take Susan sb's advice about
children myself. She's what you might call Healthy minded if you understand me."
"I understand," Mr. Craven answered. "Take Miss Mary away now and send picture to
me." When Mrs. Medlock left her at the end of her own corridor Mary flew back to
her room. She found Martha waiting there.
Martha had, in fact, hurried back after she had removed the dinner service. "I can
have my garden!" cried Mary. "I may have it
where I like! I am not going to have a govern us for a long time!
Your mother is coming to see me and I may go to your cottage! He says a little
girl like me could not do any harm and I may do what I like—
—anywhere he said Martha delightedly, "that was nice of him wasn't it?" "Martha," said Mary
solemnly, "he is really a nice man, only his face is so miserable and his
forehead is all drawn together." She ran as quickly as she could to the garden.
She had been away so much longer than she had thought she should and she knew
Dickon would have to set out early on his 5em walk. When she slipped through
the door under the ivy, she saw he was not working where she had left him. The
gardening tools were laid together under a tree. She ran to them, looking all
around the place, but there was no Dickon to be seen. He had gone away and the
secret garden was empty— —except for the robin who had just flown across the wall
and sat on a standard rose bush watching her. "He's gone," she said
woefully Oh! was he— —was he— —was he only a wood fairy?" Something white fastened to the
standard rose bush caught her eye. It was a piece of paper— —in fact, it was a piece
of the letter she had printed for Martha to send to Dickon. It was fastened on the
bush with a long thorn, and in a minute she knew Dickon had left it there. There
was some roughly printed letters on it and a sort of
picture. At first she could not tell what it was. Then she saw it was meant for a
nest with a bird sitting on it.
Underneath were the printed letters and they said: "I will come
back chapter 13 I am